<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Discursus</title>
<link>https://blog.discurs.us/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://blog.discurs.us/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Here are some things I have written down.</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 08:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Keep knowing why ML (Timeless ML Principles 2)</title>
  <dc:creator>Lucien Carroll</dc:creator>
  <link>https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2025-01-01-ml-change/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This is the second post in a series about the ways that machine learning (ML) has not changed. (The first post is <a href="../../posts/2024-12-11-ml-principles/index.html">here</a>.) Not that it is the same in every way, but that key principles from classical ML are still important today. This one is a bit of a koan: the thing that has not changed is that you should expect change, understanding it terms of ML’s purpose in your system.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/the1pony/3728761118/in/album-72157621478400640"><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2025-01-01-ml-change/tadpole1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A tadpole with hints of legs stares into the camera" width="512"></a></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A tadpole considers its existence (photo CC-ND the1pony “Oh Hai!”)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="know-why-ml-is-involved" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="know-why-ml-is-involved">Know why ML is involved</h2>
<p>When developing a product feature based on machine learning, it’s important to remember that it is a product feature first, then a software system that provides that feature, and finally an ML-based system. The primary goal—it’s reason for existence—is that it is doing something useful for your end users, in the sociotechnical context of everything else your users are using, understanding, and doing. Some software system is necessary to deliver that feature, but it might not be necessary to use any ML model at all, especially in the larval stages of exploratory user research and system prototyping, or in baseline systems used for software testing, system evaluation, and data development. If models are necessary, they are just parts in that software system body, and it might not be the same class of model as you would use at a different stage for another purpose.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/the1pony/3727958415/in/album-72157621478400640"><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2025-01-01-ml-change/tadpole2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A tadpole with little legs dangling" width="512"></a></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A tadpole prototyping some legs (photo CC-ND the1pony “Legs. I has them.”)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="a-system-has-many-parts-and-each-part-has-its-function" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-system-has-many-parts-and-each-part-has-its-function">A system has many parts, and each part has its function</h2>
<p>A function that you believe will need a big model or a custom model might be better satisfied by deterministic rules, a random function, or a much simpler model, while you focus development on the overall software system, including metrics that can guide you towards solving your users’ real needs. On the other hand, you might want to use a very large custom model or a complicated pipeline in a slow offline system that you use as a silver labeler in data development, as a teacher model for a smaller faster production model, or as a foil in system evaluation and error analysis. So think carefully about why you need ML in the system, and for each ML role in the system, consider what trade-offs are preferred among quality, latency, reliability, usability, etc.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/the1pony/3744076062/in/album-72157621478400640"><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2025-01-01-ml-change/tadpole3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="512"></a></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Tadpole with compatible legs and tail (photo CC-ND the1pony “Smiling for the camera”)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="dont-let-the-tail-wag-the-frog" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dont-let-the-tail-wag-the-frog">Don’t let the tail wag the frog</h2>
<p>A system with ML components requires additional considerations, beyond a deterministic system, but not instead of those. The non-deterministic components need their own evaluations, and the system as a whole needs end-to-end evaluation based on statistical design, beyond the end-to-end testing of logic and data formats. And resource planning and load testing will need to be tailored to the constraints of ML systems. But that is all on top of a foundation of good software development. Early exploratory user research and technical feasibility studies feed into careful designs, deterministic components are developed iteratively with classical testing, and feedback from software profiling, usability tests, and trials guide revisions to the system. But these adjustments to the architecture and development processes are for the sake of the product, for the users’ sake, not for the sake of machine learning as a goal, nor especially a particular class of model as a goal.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/the1pony/3776694971/in/album-72157621478400640"><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2025-01-01-ml-change/tadpole4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Frog with a stub of a tail, resting on a hyacinth" width="512"></a></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Frog with a legacy tail (photo CC-ND the1pony “Frog on water hyacinth: this guy still has a small tail”)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="the-only-constant-is-change" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-only-constant-is-change">The only constant is change</h2>
<p>As development progresses, the system will mature while your own understanding of the problem space matures, and your data development efforts expand and enrich your datasets. Besides the planned upgrades to models that have better quality/latency/cost profiles, you may well find that initial prototypes were focused on the wrong problem, or that you need to replace pipelines with end-to-end models for quality reasons, or replace end-to-end models with pipelines for the sake of reliabilty, speed or cost. You’ll need to find ways to adjust assumptions while allowing contrastive evaluations and error analysis.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/the1pony/3783106696/in/album-72157621478400640"><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2025-01-01-ml-change/frog.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Frog rests under a hyacinth leaf" width="512"></a></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">An adult frog prepares for new changes (photo CC-ND the1pony “frog”)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2025-01-01-ml-change/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Machine learning is evaluation all the way down (Timeless ML Principles 1)</title>
  <dc:creator>Lucien Carroll</dc:creator>
  <link>https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2024-12-11-ml-principles/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This is the first post in a series about the ways that evaluation in modern times, in the age of large language models, is still the same as in olden times. Not that it is the same in every way, but that key principles from classical machine learning evaluation are still important today.</p>
<section id="its-all-evaluation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="its-all-evaluation">It’s all evaluation</h2>
<p>The first principle is that machine learning is evaluation all the way down. You may have heard lots about training, fine-tuning, reinforcement learning, multitask learning, or other such things, which do not sound like evaluation, but really these are all evaluation too. Top to bottom, first and foremost and through to the end, it’s evaluation.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mybloodyself/1108834349/"><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2024-12-11-ml-principles/mybloodyself_turtles.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Three turtles stacked up" width="400"></a></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A tower of turtles (photo CC-BY-NC-SA 2.0 Dan Machold)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="the-foundation-is-evaluation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-foundation-is-evaluation">The foundation is evaluation</h2>
<p>The bottom turtle might be extrinsic evaluation, meaning evaluation from the outside for the purpose that the whole system is for. You need your data to be ecologically valid, comparable to data in the wild. And you need your metrics to be closely aligned with product objectives. If your system has already been unleashed in the wild, your bottom turtle might even be field testing or live metrics from regular usage. But for the sake of the privacy and safety of your users, you probably can’t or shouldn’t measure live usage in as much detail as you can in offline testing. And you probably shouldn’t depend on users to explore your system’s worst behavior. But whatever data sources you have available, your foundational evaluations should be carefully informative of what your system is doing in the wild, and carefully aligned with product goals.</p>
</section>
<section id="training-is-evaluation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="training-is-evaluation">Training is evaluation</h2>
<p>And the top turtle, or the inner loop of training, is the opposite. It can be a simplistic objective loss function evaluated on out-of-domain data. You can get a model to do something useful for you with a pretty large departure from the extrinsic data and objective. A spam filter can block new kinds of spam that were not available for training, just by generalizing from simplistic representations of email. And fundamentally, LLMs start their development evaluating predictions of the next few characters in text corpora that might or might not contain examples of the genre of text that your system is generating.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://foto.wuestenigel.com/turtle-on-a-stone/"><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2024-12-11-ml-principles/turtle_on_stone.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="One small turtle on top of various other turtles" width="400"></a></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A turtle on a turtle pile, evaluating his life choices (photo CC-BY 2.0 Marco Verch)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="there-is-lots-to-evaluate" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="there-is-lots-to-evaluate">There is lots to evaluate</h2>
<p>And in between the two ends, as you descend your turtle pile through hyperparameter selection, intrinsic evaluation of particular components and subtasks, to error analysis on the system task, you want your data to more closely match the extrinsic data and evaluation metrics at each step. As in these pictures, each turtle should be a little closer to the foundation than the one above it. Principles that I will write about later go into more depth about what this means in practice, but at a high level it means that the academic data folds of train/test splits or conventional train/dev/test splits really break out into multiple datasets with multiple splits and disaggregation dimensions.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://flickr.com/photos/nickharris1/4858787832"><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2024-12-11-ml-principles/nickharris1_turtle_pileup.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Two stacks of two turtles each" width="400"></a></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Two turtle piles (photo CC-BY-ND-2.0 Nick Harris)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It is true that LLMs add a bit more complexity here, where it’s not a single stack. You might have two stacks of turtles that merge together at the bottom, or a stack of turtles whose sole purpose is to generate data for one of the turtles in another stack. But this principle still holds: it’s all evaluation.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2024-12-11-ml-principles/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>English is a minority language too</title>
  <dc:creator>Lucien Carroll</dc:creator>
  <link>https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2022-04-03-english-minority-language/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>In California, <a href="https://www.ppic.org/publication/immigrants-in-california/">more than 1 out of 4 residents were born in another country</a>. In the San Francisco Bay Area, that number is about 1 in 3, and among tech workers in the area, <a href="https://jointventure.org/images/stories/pdf/index2018.pdf">about 3 out of 4</a>. So in tech circles, dominated by Silicon Valley, English is treated as the majority and default language, and much exposure to languages beyond English positions those other languages as foreign, personal, or home languages. Even as home languages, they are losing ground to English, <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3526379/">replaced by the second or third generation</a>. Someone who works in Silicon Valley, USA might easily think that English overwhelmingly dominates the business world, and that people who don’t use English in business life are switching to it.</p>
<p>It’s certainly true that English does have a dominant position in the global economy and in the technology world. It is spoken as the most common home language and as a national language in three of the G7 countries, and it is used as the primary trade language among speakers of many other languages. In language technology, especially in NLP research, <a href="https://thegradient.pub/the-benderrule-on-naming-the-languages-we-study-and-why-it-matters/">English is often treated as unspoken default</a>. However, the dominance of English should not be exaggerated. English accounts for a minority of the global economy, a minority of technology users, and a minority of internet content. Moreover, the dominance of English is declining.</p>
<section id="a-minority-of-economic-activity" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-minority-of-economic-activity">A minority of economic activity</h2>
<p>If you associate the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_countries_by_GDP_(nominal)">GDP of each country</a> or region to the primary language of that country/region, you can get an approximate breakdown of economic activity attributable to each language, along the lines of this table:</p>
<table class="table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Rank</th>
<th>Language</th>
<th>GDP($US Billions)</th>
<th>% of World GDP</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>1</td>
<td>English</td>
<td>24.86</td>
<td>29.59%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2</td>
<td>Chinese</td>
<td>14.73</td>
<td>17.53%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>3</td>
<td>Japanese</td>
<td>5.15</td>
<td>6.14%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>4</td>
<td>German</td>
<td>4.82</td>
<td>5.74%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>5</td>
<td>Spanish</td>
<td>4.77</td>
<td>5.67%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>6</td>
<td>French</td>
<td>3.41</td>
<td>4.06%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>7</td>
<td>Arabic</td>
<td>2.75</td>
<td>3.27%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>8</td>
<td>Portuguese</td>
<td>2.08</td>
<td>2.48%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>9</td>
<td>Italian</td>
<td>2.00</td>
<td>2.38%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>10</td>
<td>Russian</td>
<td>1.87</td>
<td>2.22%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>With the caveat that not all economic activity in a country is carried out in the dominant language, but recognizing that most economic activity in Japan, for example, is carried out in Japanese, we can make some fair generalizations. Even though English is the language accounting for the most nominal GDP, it is approximately the same sum as the next three languages combined (Chinese, Japanese and German), and the top 10 languages here account for less than 80% of the global GDP.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-minority-of-technology-users" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-minority-of-technology-users">A minority of technology users</h2>
<p>Surveys of technology users similarly show a long fat tail of preferred languages. In the <a href="https://www.internetworldstats.com/stats7.htm">internet language survey results</a> shown below, the single largest group of users do prefer English, but that number is smaller than the next two languages combined (Chinese and Spanish), and the top 10 languages together only account for 77% of the online population.</p>
<table class="table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Rank</th>
<th>Language</th>
<th>Users (millions)</th>
<th>% of World Users</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>1</td>
<td>English</td>
<td>1186</td>
<td>25.90%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2</td>
<td>Chinese</td>
<td>888</td>
<td>19.40%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>3</td>
<td>Spanish</td>
<td>364</td>
<td>7.90%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>4</td>
<td>Arabic</td>
<td>237</td>
<td>5.20%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>5</td>
<td>Portuguese</td>
<td>172</td>
<td>3.70%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>6</td>
<td>Indonesian</td>
<td>198</td>
<td>4.30%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>7</td>
<td>French</td>
<td>152</td>
<td>3.30%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>8</td>
<td>Japanese</td>
<td>119</td>
<td>2.60%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>9</td>
<td>Russian</td>
<td>116</td>
<td>2.50%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>10</td>
<td>German</td>
<td>93</td>
<td>2.00%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>If you look at surveys of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_countries_by_smartphone_penetration">smartphone penetration per country</a> and assign each population to just one language, Chinese jumps far into the lead, with English in second place.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-minority-of-internet-content" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-minority-of-internet-content">A minority of internet content</h2>
<p>A <a href="https://w3techs.com/technologies/overview/content_language">standard survey of website languages</a> reports that 62.9% of websites are in English. However, the methodology used there assigns a language according to the default of the top-level page, ignoring subdomains, so any multilingual website that sets English as the default language will count for English in the results. Methods that count web pages, such as the <a href="https://funredes.org/lc2022/V3.2.htm">Indicators of languages in the internet</a> survey produce much lower estimates of the portion of internet content in English.</p>
<table class="table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Rank</th>
<th>Language</th>
<th>Content</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>1</td>
<td>Chinese</td>
<td>21.60%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2</td>
<td>English</td>
<td>19.60%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>3</td>
<td>Spanish</td>
<td>7.85%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>4</td>
<td>Hindi</td>
<td>3.76%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>5</td>
<td>Russian</td>
<td>3.76%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>6</td>
<td>French</td>
<td>3.33%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>7</td>
<td>Portuguese</td>
<td>3.13%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>8</td>
<td>Arabic</td>
<td>3.09%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>9</td>
<td>Japanese</td>
<td>2.66%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>10</td>
<td>German</td>
<td>2.37%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>So though English is the default language in many of the most visited websites, it has dropped into second place in overall internet content. As with other tables above, this distribution also has a long fat tail. The top ten languages here account for only 71% of the surveyed content.</p>
</section>
<section id="declining-dominance" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="declining-dominance">Declining dominance</h2>
<p>Since the economies of Asia and Africa have generally been growing faster than those of Europe and North America, English accounts for a declining portion of the global economy. In addition, as digital infrastructure development extends the reach of smartphones, and of the internet more generally, the pool of technology users continues to diversify.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-left">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/NY.GDP.MKTP.KD?end=2019&amp;locations=XU-ZJ-Z7-Z4-8S-ZQ-ZG&amp;start=2010&amp;view=chart"><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2022-04-03-english-minority-language/gdp.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></a></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Global GDP by region 2010 to 2019</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>All of this means that if you are on a research team investigating language technology or on a product team developing a language-dependent system, you really need to keep a global perspective and consider multiple languages in your plan. Otherwise you will either be limiting your impact to a small portion of your potential users or very poorly serving those users.</p>
<p>Fortunately, the <em>cost</em> of localized language technology is quickly falling, making it feasible to support more languages. But that is a topic for another post.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2022-04-03-english-minority-language/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Utija’ore ñamʉ chʉ’ʉ</title>
  <dc:creator>Lucien Carroll</dc:creator>
  <link>https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2022-03-20-utijaore/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>For the past couple months, I have been studying Koreguaje (aka Coreguaje, Korebaju), working through <a href="https://www.sil.org/resources/archives/19097">Ko’rehuajʉ chʉ’ore cutuñu</a> over voice calls with a family friend as tutor. We’ve gotten about half way through the book, but as the vocabulary and grammar get more difficult, I’m finding the need to slow down. The language is a Western Tucanoan language, indigenous to the upper Caquetá river valley in Colombia, on the edge of the Amazon basin. There are a couple closely related languages in the upper Caquetá region and the neighboring corner of Ecuador, and all other languages that are known to be related to it have home territories to the east, mostly in the Vaupés. But to me it feels familiarly like an Otomanguean language. There are suprasegmental nasalization, glottalization and tone that reminds me of Mixtec, though the tone system only has high and low, without contours. And a few common words are similar enough to trip me up sometimes:</p>
<table class="table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Koreguaje</th>
<th>Mixtec</th>
<th>English</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>vʉ’e [wɨʔe]</td>
<td>ve’e [βeʔe]</td>
<td>house</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>chʉ’ʉ [tʃɨʔɨ]</td>
<td>yu’u [ʒuʔu]</td>
<td>me</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>jʉ̃jʉ̃ [hɨ̃hɨ̃]</td>
<td>jãjã [xãxã]</td>
<td>yes</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>But if you look at larger lists of comparative vocabulary, for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oto-Manguean_languages#Lexicon">Otomanguean</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tucanoan_languages#Proto-language">Tucanoan</a>, there are no such similarities. It seems that these few are coincidentally similar words, in similar sound systems.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2022-03-20-utijaore/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Wav2Vec2 Luganda</title>
  <dc:creator>Lucien Carroll</dc:creator>
  <link>https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2021-04-04-luganda-finetune/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This is a PSA for folks with an audio corpus of a low resource language: it is getting possible to build a decent speech recognition system with remarkably little transcribed data. Take this into account next time you are discussing acceptable use of new recordings, and double check how community members feel about these possibilities.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://colab.research.google.com/drive/1XxZ3mJOEXwIn-QH3C23jD_Qpom9aA1vH"><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2021-04-04-luganda-finetune/colab.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></a></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Reference and predicted text sample</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Over the past couple weekends I participated in an effort to “finetune” speech recognition models for each of the ~60 languages in the Common Voice dataset. I focused on Luganda because the languages I know more about either are not in the dataset or were well-covered by other participants. Using about 6 hours of read speech for training (i.e.&nbsp;people read sentences from public domain documents, and no separate text data was used for a language model), the <a href="https://huggingface.co/lucio/wav2vec2-large-xlsr-luganda">resulting model</a> reaches 23% word-error-rate, and considering that Bantu words are relatively long, this means it’s potentially useful for jump-starting transcription work, indexing an untranscribed audio corpus, or enabling a voice interface. It’s likely that an even lower error rate is possible using audio data from a related language for initial training, or using text data to guide the output.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2021-04-04-luganda-finetune/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 04 Apr 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Want to feel old?</title>
  <dc:creator>Lucien Carroll</dc:creator>
  <link>https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>Note: The following post was originally published as an album on Facebook. I’ve retroactively extracted it here.</em></p>
<p>I meant to post this a few weeks ago when this was going around FB/Twitter, but it’s taken a bit for me to finish writing it up. I think now is as good a time as any for some historical perspective.</p>
<section id="subtract-your-age" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="subtract-your-age">Subtract your age</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/0_twitter_clip.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Nooruddean <span class="citation" data-cites="BeardedGenius">@BeardedGenius</span>: Want to feel old? Genuinely? Minus your age from the year you were born and find a moment in history that’s closer to your birthday than now. For me it’s Hitler invading France FFS</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I am currently 41.7 years old. 83.3 years ago, on Aug 6, 1937, newly elected L.A. City Councilman <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Howard_E._Dorsey">Howard E. Dorsey</a> drove off the edge of the Rim of the World Highway, tumbled down a cliff, and died. Certainly not as notable an event as some of the other ones people are picking, but hear me out — I think there’s an apropos morality tale or two in this history.</p>
</section>
<section id="winfred-sanborn" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="winfred-sanborn">Winfred Sanborn</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/1_winfred_sanborn.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Winfred Sanborn as a middle aged man with a mustache, dressed in a suit.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The personal significance of Howard E. Dorsey’s death is not that his aunt, L.A. Schools Superintendent Susan Dorsey, gave her name to my mother’s high school, also in 1937, though that is pretty cool too. Howard Dorsey got his start as the campaign manager for my great-great-grandfather <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Winfred_J._Sanborn">Winfred Sanborn</a> (pictured), who had served as an L.A. City Councilman throughout the 1920s, and when Dorsey died, Winfred was appointed to complete his term. Winfred first joined the city council in 1919, and left the council for the second time 20 years later. A lot had changed in that time…</p>
</section>
<section id="influenza" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="influenza">Influenza</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/2_influenza.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A chart of “Influenza Cases and Deaths in Los Angeles”, a newspaper clipping from February 1919. Marked events include “Effect of Armistice Celebration”, “Effect of Thanksgiving Day” and “Effect of Christmas”.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>After careers in the postal service and undertaking, Republican Winfred Sanborn was elected in the summer of 1919, when the population of Los Angeles was just over half a million people. He is remembered in the family as a multi-talented and kind man. The Spanish Flu had just hit L.A. hard that winter, and there had been major protests and lawsuits against mandatory masks, and closures of churches, theaters and schools. By one count, 2713 people died of the flu during 1918 and 1919 in Los Angeles, about 25% of deaths over that time period.</p>
</section>
<section id="nurses-resign" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nurses-resign">Nurses Resign</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/3_nurses_resign.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Newspaper clipping: “STUDENT NURSES RESIGN One hundred and twenty-six student nurses out of 187 at the County Hospital sent in their resignations yesterday to take effect November 1, their protest to the Board of Supervisors against the admission of colored girls as student nurses having failed.”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>At the Los Angeles County Hospital, Black students had been barred from the training school for nurses, up until the previous fall. Throughout WW I the L.A. chapter of the NAACP had campaigned to open the program to Black students, on the practical matter that Black nurses could have been saving lives in the war effort. When Black student nurses were finally admitted to help with the flu epidemic, 126 white student nurses resigned in protest.</p>
</section>
<section id="not-kkk" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="not-kkk">Not KKK</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/4_not_kkk.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Newspaper clipping of picture of men lined up wearing masks, captioned: “Not Ku Klux Klan, but Draft Men Drilling in ’Flu Masks.”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Hollywood had released <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Birth_of_a_Nation">D. W. Griffith’s <em>The Birth of a Nation</em></a> just 4 years before. More widely in America, 1919 was the year of the “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_Summer">Red Summer</a>”, when riots in dozens of cities across the United States targeted Black communities. My grandfather Mario was a seven-year-old living on the outskirts of Chicago, where one of the largest massacres occurred. At least 38 people were killed, hundreds more were injured, and about 1000 Black families were left homeless. Inspired by <em>The Birth of a Nation</em> and the Red Summer, KKK membership reached 5 million people in the mid 1920s. In 1919, the LA Times could joke about soldiers in flu masks resembling a KKK rally.</p>
</section>
<section id="immigration" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="immigration">Immigration</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/5_genoveva.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Genoveva (center front) with her parents and many siblings, all dressed up</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>1919 was also the year that my five-year-old grandmother Genoveva crossed the border from Sonora, Mexico, escaping from the civil war there. The family settled in Los Angeles, west of downtown. The following decade saw dramatic immigration and growth in L.A. — the population of L.A. doubled from 1920 to 1930, while the population of Mexican Americans in the city tripled.</p>
</section>
<section id="prison-special-tour" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="prison-special-tour">Prison Special Tour</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/6_prison_special_tour.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Suffragettes address a San Francisco crowd from the back of an open carriage motorcar.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It was also in 1919 that suffragists launched the <a href="https://www.nps.gov/articles/democracy-limited-the-prison-special.htm">“Prison Special Tour”</a>, holding rallies across the country wearing prison clothes as a reminder of the prison terms that many of them had endured over the previous few years for crimes like holding open-air meetings, silently picketing the White House, and holding a banner quoting the Declaration of Independence: “Governments derive their just powers from the consent of the governed.” They were again sometimes attacked by crowd members or arrested, but it bent public attention to make it a national priority, leading to the 19th amendment, recognizing women’s right to vote, being passed by Congress and submitted to the states for ratification. It was also in 1919 that the 18th amendment was ratified, prohibiting the production and sale of alcohol. The prohibition of alcohol lead to a marked increase in corruption and mafia influence in Los Angeles. The recognition of women’s right to vote, as momentous as it was, had smaller influence, at least initially.</p>
</section>
<section id="polarization-and-inequality" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="polarization-and-inequality">Polarization and inequality</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/7_dw_nominate.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Mean DW-NOMINATE Difference for House versus Top One Percent Income Share, 1923-2012</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>1919 was also a crest in political polarization and income inequality. Through the roaring 20s, income inequality creeped further up, while political polarization started to fall, perhaps broken by the patriotism surrounding WW I. It was finally the New Deal policies of the Great Depression, and the patriotically high taxes of the WW II war effort that brought inequality back down, and laid the foundation for the shared prosperity of the post-war boom.</p>
</section>
<section id="president-wilson" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="president-wilson">President Wilson</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/8_wilson_ticket.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Image of entry ticket: “This ticket entitles W. J. Sanborn to one seat on the platform; PRESIDENT WILSON MEETING; Shrine Auditorium; Saturday, September 20th, 1919”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>One of Winfred’s first official activities was welcoming President Wilson on his arrival to Los Angeles in September 1919, part of Wilson’s campaign to gain support for forming the League of Nations. Wilson’s health was already failing (possibly from complications of the flu), and he would have a debilitating stroke in October. Also in October he was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize for his efforts to form the League of Nations, but in his weakened state, he was unsuccessful in convincing the United States to join, and the United States turned towards isolationism.</p>
</section>
<section id="l.a.-river-crossings" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="l.a.-river-crossings">L.A. River Crossings</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/9_viaduct.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Historical photo of the 9th Street viaduct across the Los Angeles River</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>With the exception of the rising corruption, none of these issues seem to have been major concerns of Winfred’s years on the city council. I like to imagine his experience in the undertaking industry during the flu epidemic must have influenced his decision to run for city council, and one of his committee memberships was the Public Health and Sanitation committee. But his primary motive and major effort throughout the 1920s was on improving the transportation system, especially in connecting East L.A. to downtown, such as the system of viaducts crossing the L.A. river, including the 9th Street crossing shown here.</p>
</section>
<section id="betty-hill" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="betty-hill">Betty Hill</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/10_betty_hill.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Activist Betty Hill (left) with other members of the Republican Women’s Study Club.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In 1926, the Los Angeles Playground Commission officially <a href="https://la.curbed.com/2019/8/19/20757888/betty-hill-segregation-pools">segregated most of the public swimming pools in the city</a>. For the “public welfare”, swimming pools were designated for whites only except for one day a week, called “colored day” or “international day”. Activist Betty Hill (pictured on left) was affiliated with the NAACP but carried out most of her activism through her neighborhood association and a group she started, called the Republican Women’s Study Club. Immediately after the decision was made to segregate the swimming pools and for the next five years, Betty Hill led a series of boycotts and lawsuits to push the city to reverse the decision. Initial judicial rulings allowed the segregation on “separate but equal” grounds, because there was one swimming pool in the city that allowed children of all races throughout the week. Finally in 1931, a judge ruled that the city had to integrate the swimming pools. Three times the city council voted on whether to contest the ruling, twice while Winfred was in office and once after he left. Each time, the city narrowly declined to contest the ruling. I don’t know how Winfred voted, and it was not a significant issue in that election. Similar practices of “Mexican Mondays” at public pools were known elsewhere in California, <a href="https://scholarworks.lib.csusb.edu/history-in-the-making/vol3/iss1/4/">as late as 1944 in San Bernardino</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="deportations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="deportations">Deportations</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/11_deportations.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Deportees lined up in Central Station, headed for Mexico.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The primary issues of the 1931 election were about public versus private ownership of the city utilities. Winfred was not strongly on either side of the issue, but he was opposed by the Police Chief James Davis (who at least initially was intent on reforming the city government) and he lost his re-election campaign. 1931 was also a difficult year all-around. 16 year-old Genoveva had dropped out of school the year before, to help support the family. There were bread lines and hunger marches, and Los Angeles County <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mexican_Repatriation">deported legal residents and even many citizens to Mexico</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="light-festival" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="light-festival">Light Festival</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/12_light_festival.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Light festival celebrating arrival of electricity from Hoover Dam.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>By 1937, when Winfred Sanborn was reappointed to the city council, Los Angeles had reached 1.5 million people. The first LA freeway was under construction, and electricity from the Hoover Dam had just reached the city the year before, prompting the light festival shown in the picture. By 1940, L.A. would be pulling its drinking water all the way from Mono Lake, beyond Yosemite.</p>
</section>
<section id="lapd-bombings" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lapd-bombings">LAPD Bombings</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/13_clinton_raymond.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Clifford Clinton and Harry Raymond</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The corruption in city goverment had reached a crisis point. In October 1937, the L.A. Police bombed the house of Clifford Clinton, a grand jury member who was leading an investigation of Mayor Frank Shaw. In January 1938, the LAPD then bombed the car of Harry Raymond, a private investigator working with Clinton. The picture shows Clinton and Raymond after the second bombing.</p>
</section>
<section id="los-angeles-police-department" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="los-angeles-police-department">Los Angeles Police Department</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/14_lapd_parade.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">LAPD officers on motorcycles lined up for a parade</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>When it was clear that the LAPD was responsible, Mayor Shaw was recalled from office, and the successor, Mayor Bowron worked with the grand jury to remove Police Chief Davis and clean the corruption out of the police department and city government. He also appointed the first African American and the first woman to the police commission. Winfred was not particularly associated with either Mayor Shaw or Mayor Bowron, but due to the anti-incumbent mood, he was not re-elected in 1939.</p>
</section>
<section id="interracial-marriage" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="interracial-marriage">Interracial Marriage</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/15_interracial_marriage.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Excerpt of Perez et al v. Sharp, challenging California laws against interracial marriage</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In 1948, the year after Winfred died and the year before his granddaughter, my Grandma Lynette got married, the California Supreme Court ruled that the Los Angeles County Clerk could not deny a marriage license to Mexican American Andrea Perez and African American Sylvester Davis, finding that California’s laws against mixed race marriages were unconstitutional. 20 years later, the US Supreme Court ruled that all such state laws were unconstitutional. Still it was 30 more years, the same year I graduated high school, before a narrow majority of US residents approved of interracial marriages.</p>
</section>
<section id="equal-rights-amendment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="equal-rights-amendment">Equal Rights Amendment</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/16_equal_rights_amendment.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Protestors carrying a banner with the words of the proposed Equal Rights Amendment: “Equality of rights under the law shall not be denied or abridged by the United States or by any state on account of sex.”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The same women who championed the 19th amendment in 1919 introduced the Equal Rights Amendment in 1923. It was finally passed in Congress 50 years later with wide bipartisan support, but the process stalled out during ratification. In January 2020, Virginia became the 38th state to finally ratify the amendment, which would have been the criterion for enacting it, but because of expired deadlines and revoked ratifications, the status of the Equal Rights Amendment is still in limbo.</p>
</section>
<section id="history-is-still-here-with-us" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="history-is-still-here-with-us">History is still here with us</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/17_winfred_smiling.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Winfred J. Sanborn as a smiling old man</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>To be terribly unsubtle, here are some lessons I see:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>History has changed so much and yet it is still here with us. The children of my grandmothers’ generation–who were taught that it was a health risk to swim with Black kids and that Mexican American kids belong in Mexico, and shouldn’t marry each other–overcame enormous obstacles and their own prejudices to create the good old days of my generation’s childhood.</li>
<li>The arc of history that “<a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2012/11/15/arc-of-universe/">bends towards justice</a>” is loooong, and doesn’t bend on its own. People bend it.</li>
<li>The smart and nice people we often admire, who take centrist views on the issues of the day, are essential for a civil society, but they won’t be the leaders who bend history towards justice. Though they may well be the deciding vote when the tide changes.</li>
<li>If you, like me, are one of those people who like civil society, take a good hard look at what your positions will look like in 50 or 100 years. Use the influence you have to make history step lively towards justice.</li>
<li>The current levels of polarization and inequality are serious problems, but they can be fixed. We need to remind each other that we are on one team against the forces that threaten to destroy human society, find common ground, and work together like we are fighting a war–not with each other, but with poverty, climate change, dehumanization, etc.</li>
<li>Elections matter, but they are just the beginning. If you don’t like your options, make your favorite options happen. If you do like your options, don’t count on your heroes to do the right thing. They are human too, and may need some prodding from time to time.</li>
<li>This epidemic will pass. Eventually enough of us will be doing some combination of masking+distancing+testing+tracing that the uncontrolled spread will be stopped. Let’s get there ASAP, and don’t let racism and classism compound the problem. We are literally all in this together.</li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://blog.discurs.us/posts/2020-11-01-feel-old/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
